[Music]
all right welcome to the session with
the title what's new introducing the
business foundation and the number
series module my name is yesper Schulz V
and I'm an architect on the business
Central team most of my time I spent
driving the GitHub codevelopment um
story forward but I'm also very engaged
in the componentization of the business
application which is what we're going to
talk about here today and to help me
with that I've brought Andreas thank you
yeah um Andreas I've worked on business
Central for the past 10 years been
working both on application and in
client right now I'm focusing on system
application and business Foundation that
we're going to talk about
today all right so let's jump into it
what are we going to talk about today
I'm going to be spending a few minutes
introducing the business Foundation why
do we need it and how did we create it
and then Andreas is going to tell you a
little bit more about the first module
that we have in the business Foundation
which is the number series module why
did we pick that module which user
experience improvements did we make what
are the changes to the API and how do
you need to uptake those changes is the
main topic that that andr is going to
cover and then we're going to wrap up
with a very short call to action and
call it a day so let's start with a
small story and for that we need to go
all the way back to the beginning well
not all the way back to the big bang no
dinosaurs is also a little bit too far
back here we go some of you will
remember this good old Dynamics
nav if you go 7 years back in time uh
you would find something like this
there's a monolith application which has
grown organically over the past 25
years local versions were all built as
modifications to our W1 the so-called
worldwide
version and before you could implement
the solution at a partner sorry at a
customer side you would add
verticalization customer modifications
and so on so no two implementations of
Dynamics would be
identical so the beginning of the story
that I want to tell today starts with
introduction of extend iions or as we
call them today apps so the introduction
of apps started a paradigm shift where
we went from uh the good old code
customization model to the new
extensibility
model and Microsoft as part of that
formulated a goal that we all need to
get rid of the customizations in favor
of apps of different sies and shape uh
shapes and
sizes and you were asked to convert your
code into repeatable apps going either
to appsource or uh into pte per tenent
extensions I guess you're all following
along so far so that idea was launched
and you know everything was Bliss
everything is great you know woohoo
moving forward well maybe that is
idealizing the facts a little bit here
because with the transition out of
customizations and into apps new
challenges arose and if you've ever
built an app which you probably have
you'll recognize some of these
challenges I
hope so maybe you want to build an app
uh but you don't really have access to
the right places where you can hook into
the base product it might be missing
some interfaces or an event or even some
public procedures so if you've ever been
to an Al app extensions the repository
where you can log extensibility requests
you'll know exactly what I
mean and then one thing is you know that
you don't have the right places to hook
into but also the features that were
built for code customization model
aren't necessarily built with a
extensibility in mind so the feature is
not really designed to be extended it's
a challenge too that we
Face also we still have many subvariants
to cater for I guess the most common uh
subvariant is localizations that you're
all aware of so just because you built
an extension that works great in the
North American version doesn't
necessarily mean that it works fantastic
with the German version as well so
that's a challenge that we run into as
well and then there is the undocumented
apis so even if you find the place you
know where you want to hook into um
there is no real documentation there's
nothing for you to read you know how
does this system behave exactly at this
point in the in the code so what you in
in reality need to do is you need to
read the code to understand um how it's
working which can be extremely time
consuming
and sometimes also because it's not very
clear where you need to hook into you
might tap into uh hooking into
implementation details and those are
very very hard to spot and the problem
is when you do that then you know the
chances are the product will change and
your extension is going to break so all
of these were challenges that came with
us formulating the goal of moving to an
extensibility
model um to address these
changes um the business Central team
decided to re-engineer uh the
application from the bottom up so we
wanted to break the monolith so to speak
and reimagine the application as a
collection of smaller functionally
coherent
modules and that's how the system
application was born which has been
around for a couple of years now um
which in reality just is a collection of
small modules small apps combined into
this new logical
layer so now I'm mentioning modules
let's remind ourselves what's a module
because that is also what we're using
for uh the business foundation in
essence um module is just a set of
objects the difference to other sets of
objects though is that these need to be
functionally
coherent modules separate concerns and
that's the first property really of a of
a module it's coherence so how do we
separate concerns and ensure coherence
we split the functionality into an app
of its own so bottom line a module is an
extension so why are we not calling it
extension well it's because we're at the
bottom layer and we're not really
extending anything here so we came up
with a name module but think of it just
as an
app but there are a few more properties
to it than just
that um one of the key differences is
that a module encapsulates complexity by
using the access modifiers we keep the
implementation details hidden away you
cannot access these um so but that gives
us the freedom to change the internal
implementation at will without risking
breaking you uh as it was the case
before then how do you access those
internal you know workings well we
provide you with a facade which is a
stable API that is not going to change
it has nice XML code documentation so
that you now no longer need to read the
inner workings or understand the inner
workings of a module you simply need to
understand the documentation on the
facade and you'll be able to consume
this module which is a much much better
place to be than where we came from so
summing up the advantages of a module
they separate concerns they are
functionally
coherent uh they have stable well
documented apis exposed through facades
they encapsulate complexity and hide
implementation
details they have a smaller attack
surface which makes them easier for us
to
secure they are faster to compile which
is a very very nice side
effect and also very important
particularly to me is that their size
and clear purpose allows for more
focused uh um discussions and hence also
make them more suitable for an
contribution model which is very much
what we're looking
at they're also easier to Performance
Monitor and test and at some point they
also will allow for individual
versioning and effective upgrading we're
not there yet but at least they are
prepared for that so also I don't lately
there's been a lot of talk about solid
so I figured I mentioned some of the
points here uh solid are the first five
principles of object oriented design um
so a module out of the box uh supports
single responsibility principle meaning
it has you know only this one
responsibility it has the open close
principle meaning um that it's open for
extension but it's closed for
modifications um you don't necessarily
need to implement the interfaces if you
don't want to and so on and so forth so
it's a good step in the right direction
gos into the object oriented
world so now that the system application
was was introduced everything is bliss
again right now we're there everything's
great again I'm afraid that that's not
entirely the truth because the
introduction of the system application
brought its own set of challenges with
it so first of all um even though the
new layer was architecturally superior
to the old monolith um the process of
ripping out capabilities unfortunately
left a lot of dependent apps broken um
so breaking changes were everywhere when
we first introduced uh the system
application and it quickly became
apparent that we cannot keep working
like this especially not if we want to
get into the more should we say business
focused processes such as number series
because we would just be breaking
everyone and impose a huge amount of
work with every release that we would
make where we would build these modules
so we needed to come up with some
solutions um and two of these you should
know if not let's quickly repeat them
the first one is that in the beginning
an app took a dependency directly on the
base
application and directly on the system
application and that means if something
moved from the base app to the syst
application you would have to update
your apps it's a breaking change we
hence introduced application
redirection which means that all of our
logical layers come underbrella an
umbrella called application which you
find in the app Json and if you take a
dependency on the application its
entirety now uh things can move between
all the apps that are under this
application umbrella so that was the
first thing we needed to do now
unfortunately as you will also see later
when Andreas is talking about the API
changes that we decided to make for a
very good reason sometimes we do need to
make changes and we do need to you know
go away from something old to get to a
better place um but of course that needs
to be announced so when we move some
things out of the base application into
a different logical layer and we want
the old implementation to go away uh
then we of course needed to have an uh
some way of of conveying that
information so we introduced the
deprecation scheme where we're going to
tell inversion this and this and that
this is going away and this is
coming um this you should
also be know by now we've been doing
that for a couple of releases is
now but um you know ideally we do not
want to deprecate because deprecation Al
always also inflicts work on on you the
partners um so it should be the last
resort um and you know having things
under this application umbrella as I
mentioned was the first step because now
you can move just about all objects
between
apps but there was one object that you
couldn't move and those were tables so
table when they had to be moved needed
to run up upgrade code and the old table
need to be deprecated and so on so forth
with 2024 wave 1 um that's a thing of
the past at least in this version
Microsoft is able to move tables between
apps without being breaken so all the
apps depending on uh the table object
will be blissfully unaware that the
table has moved logical layer and that
was a prerequisite for us to be able
to um well move ahead in our
componentization
efforts so um given those capabilities
we're now ready to tackle the more
should we say embedded modules um and
that's why we felt we're ready to
introduce the business Foundation which
squeezes neatly in between the base
application and the system
application very quickly it is a
horizontal Erp related functionality
which is used by all on none of the
application domains so it's all these
General Erp Concepts that you will find
there Builders modules as we talked
about there will not be localizations um
if we need localizations we're going to
make
extensions um it's developed with zero
depth we're developing it the way that
we want uh the system architecture to be
and all the tables are going to be moved
in non-breaking way so what's the
business Foundation then well as an
example you know we could say address
management currency management Dimension
management which a very interesting one
so it has all these management things um
given time but we need to start
somewhere and uh for that we chose to
start with number series
management and there are some good
reasons for that which Andreas is going
to cover uh in a minute I just want to
make one final you know important
statement here and that is that uh
everything that you see here today was
developed as true open source it's the
first module that we developed as true
open source uh and that means that if
you go to uh GitHub you'll be able to
find introducing the new business
Foundation layer and you can see you
know we had like uh
246 conversations uh with the community
about you know how how should this be
developed or or like changes that are
needed um and I think we ended up with
like 250 commits yes um so you can go
here and you can read all the Gory
details look into all the code reviewing
process that Andreas went through before
deciding that now this is ready for
release and we think we've covered our
basis and everyone should be happy with
this um so that's a great change and we
hope to be of course seeing much more uh
of that that way of co-developing our
features in the
future well that was it for me uh so
Andreas why don't you tell us a little
about why we chose number series yes
thank you so let's talk about why we
chose number series well number Series
has a high uptake around the product so
that means it's useful both for us and
for you as partners it's also not too
big or too small so we want something
that we can actually move but that also
brings business value uh to it and it
has a great opportunity for improvement
because it's been patched around quite a
lot so here we have a lot of things we
can really improve furthermore there are
also tables that we are going to move
and that this way we get to verify that
we can move tables which in the end will
benefit you uh as partners who can now
go ahead and in the future will be able
to move your tables as
well now let's take a look at how does
this actually look inside of business
Central so you're probably all familiar
with business Central and in here I can
and go to the number series page when
I'm here you'll see there's a few new
options um in here we both have an open
lines fact box as well as a relationship
fact box which allows you to very
quickly see what are the open lines for
your different number series and what
relationships have you set up so you
don't have to drill in for every single
one in order to find these as well as
we've also promoted these action so it's
very easy to
access on top of that we've also add
this ability to see expiring number
series what we mean by that is these are
number series that don't have any open
lines or are in warning State what I
mean by warning state is you know on the
number series lines we have this warning
number if the last number used is within
that warning number then we also going
to show that so in other words these are
lines these are number series that you
want to take action on before they run
out or you can't use the product
properly furthermore we've also been
working on improving our error messages
so we've actually in the new API that
we've introduced all the error messages
are now actionable error messages so to
show you an example of that I can go to
the customer number series and let's say
we close this number Series so I'm just
going to copy the last number used here
to the ending number which means now I
can no longer create any customers so if
I go now to my customer list and I say
create a new customer you will see I get
the error you cannot assign any new
numbers from the number series cost now
because I have permissions to set up
number series I'm presented with an
actionable error message that allows me
to go into the number series lines see
those and I can fix that in here so now
I click open num series lines I'm
presented with the number series for
customer and I can see oh this one ended
so maybe I want to update the ending
number or more likely that you want to
provide another number series line in
here so in this case let's say we
started
from C 100 uh yeah and let's now go back
into the customers create a new customer
and everything works I can create my
customer call Andreas leave and without
leaving the customer list I was able to
actually go and fix this right away uh
without having to first go number series
find the correct number series go to
lines fix that and then go all the way
back so this is one of the very nice
fixes and as I mentioned we've actually
updated all our error messages in the
new API to use these actionable error
messages so you can go and fix it right
away so I've been talking a lot about
the new API so how does that actually
look so let's take a look over in in
vsod code and take a look at the code
itself before we actually dive too much
into the code I want to quickly talk
about why did we actually decide to
rewrite this to create a new
API and if we take a look at the old
implementation we will see here in
number series management is the one that
used we have a lot of functions and it's
not always obvious what function you
want to use for instance for getting the
next number which is the most used
functionality of number series that's
its purpose uh we have the function get
next number get next number three to get
next
number we have get next number one we
have get next number two try get next
number get next number after run and
yeah so basically there's a lot of
functionality for just getting the next
number and as a new person what should I
actually be using and how does these do
these work furthermore if you look at du
get next number we have this parameter
modify series and that what this does is
you can provide this with fults which
means you actually just want to see what
is the next number without updating the
number series however you can also use
it to batch your changes so that's
another reason to set the this to Falls
to get a bunch of numbers and then save
all of those in one go so this does
multiple things and there's several
things to be aware of that I'm not going
to go into details about here but it's
uh quite uh you have to really be
careful of what you're doing here and I
assume none of this was documented
before right I mean you would have to
guess which one or read the code to
understand which one of these five or
six options you have to choose yeah it's
not very clear what what you want to do
exactly so now instead we have split
this into two code units that we want to
use so we have the number series and
number series batch code units that this
has been split
into mainly you want to use the number
Series code unit this code unit is your
main goto it contains get next number
get Peak next number get last number
used and it updates the DAT space right
away whenever you get a number and it
just works out of the box and as you can
see I already mentioned pnx number so we
no longer have this modifi parameter for
get next number if you want to check
what the next number is you simply call
pick next number and we're not going to
update anything in the background or
keep any state about that furthermore
there's a bunch of helper functions as
you can see here for instance you can
check whether two number Ser are related
or you can look up the related number
Series so uh let the user pick a related
number
series now we also have the batch code
unet as I mentioned batch is what you
want to use whenever you get whenever
you want to get a lot of different
numbers in very quickly after each
other the batch is going to keep the
state in memory whenever you get numbers
and only save at the very end when you
call Save State it has the exact same
functions as the number service cun so
you can get next number Peck next number
get less number
used um and of course it's going to be
all based on this number you can get
numbers from different number series
from different dates you can run out of
one line and run into the next line and
it's going to have handle all of that
for you and just at the very end call
Save State and we'll save all of these
back to disk and this is the most
performant so when you need performance
for getting numbers this is the go-to
code
unit finally we have this function
simulate get next number that previously
was hardcoded in a lot of different
places basically you have a number this
was usually on journals that you want to
for the next line you want to increment
the document number by one but you
didn't want to actually increment the
number series itself you just want to
say hey based on this was the previous
number please give me the next number
and that's exactly what this does you
provided a number service as well as a
usch date and what should it assume the
last number was and then it's going to
give you the next number without
updating anything in the number series
itself so this is quite useful and I'll
show you some example of where you
actually want to start using this as
well now this is basically how you would
use number series but what if you have
your own implementation like let's say
you want to override some how something
work or you want to um basically you
want to control how we get numbers in
that case we have this enum called
number series implementation which
specifies what are all the
implementations for number series and in
here you can add your own implementation
as well as provide the implementation
details so use this interface here and
then it will show up in business Central
so this interface is very easy to use
actually we have three main functions
which are pick next number get next
number and get last number used very
clear what they do and finally we have
whether your implementation is likely to
produce gaps and this is because some
business scenarios are not allowed to
produce gaps so we need to know that so
we can show this to the
user now once you have added that you
can actually go back into business
Central and your implementation is going
to show up here in the implementation
column you can now switch to your
implementation instead and start using
that that's it for the implementation
now I've talked a lot about how the new
API looks right so you're probably
wondering how about do I need to upake
this right away is the previous stuff
gone is it still going to work how long
does it work for and so on so first of
all there are no breaking changes in
this we are using the normal Absolution
process as for every other feature in
business Central that you're hopefully
familiar with that means the old Legacy
code has been obsoleted with version 24
and will be removed with version 27 so
that means until then the old
functionality is still going to remain
functional and work exactly the way it
is of course we have already converted
all the Microsoft code to use the new
API now how do we actually use this new
API so let's take a look into how you
would actually start using that first of
all we have in case you have this
delayed insert so you get that next
number but you actually don't want to
modify it yet because here we are just
checking whether the next number is
equal to your document number and in
that case well then we want to save it
here you can simply use batch you say
just get next number and if that is the
document number you want you can modify
uh you can save this state of course you
could also use Pig next number if it's
not important to update the number
series
afterwards furthermore we've also made
some things much much simpler so some of
you might be familiar with our batch
posting in here we have this number
series management which is an array of
100 uh yeah number series
managements and we use all of these in
order to Cache the number series and not
fetch them multiple times from the
database and get performance out of that
however this is not this quite
convoluted it's not very simple to do in
other places and basically it doesn't
look too nice and we have a limitation
of 100 number series now you're probably
not going to run out of that but why
have a limitation in the first place
with the new API all you need to do is
create a number series Batch get the
next number and save State at the end as
I mentioned before it's going to handle
if you change number series if you run
out of one line and run into the next
line change dates and all of that is
going to have handled automatically
next we have some examples where we are
now more explicit so for instance or
actually the init series function has
been completely removed because it's not
super clear what is going on in this
case this for the bank account where we
actually want to first set up the number
series and then get the next number what
is actually happening which is much more
readable down here in the new code is we
are actually checking whether the GL
bank account number series is related to
the number series of the previous record
if it is well then we want to continue
using that number series otherwise we
want to fall back to the bank account
number series setup in the GL setup and
then afterwards just get the next number
as usual so this is a bit a few more
lines but now you can see what is
actually happening and for new
developers this is easier to uh read and
understand finally we have this simulate
next number as I mentioned in a lot of
places we have this functionality this
is taken from the general journal batch
as you can probably see where we have
the last document number and now we want
to create a new line so we want to
figure out what should the next number
be in here we call into number series
management to figure out what line to
use then we check whether that
increments by more than one if it does
we call back into number series
management and ask it to increment the
number by this amount otherwise we just
do an ink string and if the number
series doesn't exist we again uh just
increment by one this again is going to
be much simpler you can simply call
simulate get next number given that the
previous number was this document number
number and this number series please
increment it and you will get the new
number without having to do all of these
hacks and yeah I want to just quickly
highlight you'll see here on GitHub we
have this refactoring to use the new
number series module and this one
provides examples of how to uptake the
new code and we would love to help if
there's any other things that we need of
examples please uh reach out and we can
update this document and make it much
simpler for you guys to uptake this new
uh number series module and that's it
for me back over to you Yesa thank you
very much Andreas for this very detailed
Deep dive into the world of number
series um so we only have a few minutes
left here so quick call to action very
important one though please start
uptaking these changes now don't wait
until we actually remove the old number
series Legacy API because do get next
number series and try get next number
they are going away because they make no
sense so get on the Forefront you know
make the refactorings and as Andrea said
we are always eager to help you know
just let us know if we forgot anything
and we'll be there to assist
you and if we might have forgotten
something in the API because you did not
know that this was codeveloped on GitHub
you know the code is still out there on
GitHub you can just go there and you can
add to the API you can suggest changes
and so on and so forth let us know what
is missing and uh we can work together
on making this the best number series
module that we possibly
can now we talked about code development
but there's one code that we didn't
really mention co-pilot so where's that
well we didn't get around to do the
co-pilot support quite yet um but our
MVP Demitri catson picked up on that and
said like hey now we have this new
awesome module I would like to
contribute and make a uh co-pilot
support for this one so he is actively
working on that if you go to the bcfs
repository into issue 659 you can see
the entire discussion going on and very
very soon theit is going to post this
first pull request and you can tag along
on how co-pilot is implemented uh for
this brand new module so if you want to
learn something here's your opportunity
and then also of course componentization
of our base application is going to
continue
um we have not really landed yet on
which are the next modules we also need
to focus on co-pilot to a large degree
um but we are going to continue um so
keep your eyes open for new pull
requests on GitHub because of course
it's going to be developed out
there and that was it from us um thank
you very much for sticking with us and
learning about number series and the
business foundation and I really hope to
see you on GitHub um so see you there
thank you see
you